<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Agile on A blog by Harry McCarney</title>
    <link>https://harrymccarney.com/tags/agile/</link>
    <description>A blog by Harry McCarney (Agile)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://harrymccarney.com/tags/agile/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How Quality Control processes can undermine quality</title>
      <link>https://harrymccarney.com/post/how-quality-control-processes-can-undermnine-quality/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://harrymccarney.com/post/how-quality-control-processes-can-undermnine-quality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Software must now evolve faster than ever. Underlying technology such as cloud infrastructure, operating systems and programming languages now receive near continuous updates from Google, Microsoft, Amazon, and the open source community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, competition between software providers has intensified. Increasing customer expectations require companies to rapidly ‘test and learn’ to find and maintain their markets. Most critically, the security landscape is generating serious new threats almost weekly that previously would occur monthly or annually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many organisations, particularly in regulated industries, rely on release processes that were originally designed to maintain quality when the pace of the change was slower. As the need for updates speeds up, some have reached a tipping point and can no longer keep up. Their backlog of critical fixes expands exponentially and the release speed slows in unison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At H&amp;amp;C, we know that maintaining software through regular small updates is easier than large staged releases. Staged releases contain many simultaneous updates, which cause interdependencies that multiply the complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Engineering managers in large organisations are understandably risk averse. They rightly place the burden of proof on the claim that leaner quality control processes are essential for creating quality. This blog provides an explanation of this, and ideas on how we can begin to design more effective quality control processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-systems-are-unstable&#34;&gt;Why systems are unstable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systems are a union of form and context. As context is constantly evolving, complex systems can never be stable. The ‘form’ of a system refers to its set of formal rules and features. In a software system, this could be the business logic, user experience, interface design or algorithms. The ‘context’ refers to all factors that the form must interact with. In a software system, this includes the cloud environment, user requirements, technical proficiency of the user, connection speeds, current security threats and competitor products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quality of a software system is a measure of the closeness of the fit between the form and its surrounding context. The challenge all systems face is the constant evolution of the context. In recent years the pace of this evolution has accelerated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These changes in context lead to misfits with the form. Initially, misfits are seen as edge cases but as the fit between form and context comes apart the system becomes inoperable. System maintenance must identify and patch these misfits so that the form evolves in tandem with the context. Due to the constantly evolving nature of the context this amounts to a Sisyphean game of ‘whack-a-mole’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;complexity-does-not-increase-linearly&#34;&gt;Complexity does not increase linearly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effort required to resolve these misfits does not increase linearly with each new misfit. The interdependence between misfits in different areas of any system multiplies its complexity. Even if that interdependence is not strictly formal, the practical human effort to make multiple simultaneous changes to a system increases exponentially with the number of changes that need to be made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many developments within software engineering such as the single responsibility principle (SRP) and Microservice Architecture are designed to address this problem. The hope is that breaking the system down into small independent parts will prevent complexity buildups as misfits remain local to an individual component. However, microservices are subsystems that, by definition, have complex interdependencies, which require careful planning and simultaneous updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://harrymccarney.com/SystemDebtDiagrams.png&#34; alt=&#34;ComplexityandLinkages&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figures 1-3 show the complexity increasing as the number of misfits and corresponding fixes increase. Each box represents a version of the system, similar to a code branch containing a fix for a specific misfit. A is the current production system and the other boxes are discrete versions. Simultaneous changes (these are necessary if the number of misfits increase), create exponential complexity as every branch must be compatible with every other. This is in contrast to Figure 4 in which the changes are made fast enough to avoid a build up and can therefore be made linearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cognitive load of addressing the complexity is a factor of the number of links in the release. The links are depicted as double ended arrows. Figure 3 has ten links between the components, while Figure 4 has just four. This can be formalised as C = L², where C is complexity and L is the number of links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relationship between complexity and interdepency in simultaneous updates creates the phenomenon that a linear rewrite of a system from scratch is often simpler than patching an existing system. This leads to a difficult conversation between engineers and Management, who seldom grasp the practical implications of this type of complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;release-cycles-must-keep-pace-with-context-changes-to-prevent-a-build-up-in-complexity&#34;&gt;Release cycles must keep pace with context changes to prevent a build up in complexity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://harrymccarney.com/MisfitGraphs.png&#34; alt=&#34;Release cycle&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 5 shows the different stages in a release cycle of a system. The length of &amp;lsquo;Time to Live&amp;rsquo; is fixed by the organisation’s internal processes. Each stage contributes to the Time to Live, but in organisations that are struggling with quality issues, the ‘Fix Validated’ stage tends to increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As release cycles lengthen they also become less elastic. This means the Time to Live takes approximately the same amount of time regardless of the scale of the fix currently being pushed through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other pivotal interval in the diagram is the Misfit Frequency. This is the time between each context update that goes on to create a new misfit to be addressed. To prevent the build up in complexity, the Time to Live must be shorter than the Misfit Frequency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Misfit Frequency will vary widely from system to system. The printing presses changed very slowly until the information age. Now every blog platform must regularly and reactively release fixes for new versions of the major browsers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This step change in the evolution speed of context presents serious challenges to transforming organisations. Those that are moving from the relatively slow moving hardware medium to the more rapid software medium, or from installable software to the cloud, find their release processes are too slow to keep up with the context evolution and resulting misfit frequency. This leads to a build up of complexity that quickly swamps the organisation and erodes the quality of their systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;expanding-quality-control-processes-is-counter-productive-if-the-release-cycle-becomes-too-slow&#34;&gt;Expanding Quality Control processes is counter productive if the release cycle becomes too slow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An understandable reaction from management to seeing poor quality systems go into production is to question why there weren&amp;rsquo;t more checks in place to prevent this happening. This often results in adding yet more layers of checks, rather than fine tuning of the existing ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads to a proliferation of overlapping quality processes, which slow the speed at which misfits can be resolved. Eventually process overheads reach critical mass, pushing the project into a vicious circle of increasing complexity and bureaucratic paralysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the nature of complexity, quality is directly correlated to how fast a system can get a misfit fix into production. However, it is also clear that engineers do make mistakes and that some form of checking prior to going live is essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automated testing was developed as a response to the need for rapid large scale testing. In practice some form of manual testing should always be part of the fail safe. However, the utility of the manual process depends on both its accuracy in identifying detects and, crucially, the delay it creates in Time to Live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The accuracy of a validation stage can be formalised as a probability of detecting a defect if one is present. After a certain threshold of defect detection probability is achieved, any further expansion of validation processes gives diminishing returns, slows the Time to Live, builds up complexity and thereby decreases quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-quality-of-a-system-is-determined-by-the-ratio-between-the-time-it-takes-to-deploy-a-fix-and-the-speed-at-which-the-context-generates-the-need-for-new-fixes&#34;&gt;The quality of a system is determined by the ratio between the time it takes to deploy a fix, and the speed at which the context generates the need for new fixes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we have seen, it is essential to avoid the simultaneous changes caused by a build up of unaddressed misfits. We can formulate this understanding of the relationship between quality, validation processes, and the time it takes to get a fix into production as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quality (Q): The closeness of the fit between form and context. 
Misfit Frequency (MF): The time interval between each misfit. 
Time to Live (TTL): TIme interval from discovery of misfit to deployment into production.
Defect Detection: The probability (expressed as number between 0 and 1) of the quality control process uncovering a defect in a new release addressing a misfit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q = (MF / TTL) * DD&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While simplistic, this equation does give insight into the real relationship between these variables and shows how we can begin to optimise for quality. It shows that TTL must be less than MF in order to prevent the build up of misfits and the paralysing complexity that comes with it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sample calculations could include, where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TTL = 5 days
MF = 8 days
DD = 80% chance of spotting defects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(8/5) * 0.8 = Quality 1.28&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critically, if we adjust these variables slightly to make the Time to Live longer at seven days, almost at a misfit rate, we get a quality score of 1.02.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the Time to Live exceeds the Misfit Frequency then quality very rapidly deteriorates. For example, where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TTL = 15 days
MF = 8 days
DD = 95% chance of spotting defects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gives a quality score of 0.5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://harrymccarney.com/QualitybyDefectDetection.png&#34; alt=&#34;Quality by Defect Dectection&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This graph shows how quality decreases once the Defect Detection probability increases above a certain point. It assumes that each 10% increase in the DD rate adds one unit onto the Time to Live. It illustrates that lengthy release processes cause an exponential increase in complexity which will inevitably lead to a decrease in quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;quality-control-processes-must-be-lean&#34;&gt;Quality control processes must be lean&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A proper understanding of complexity and its root causes necessitates a release process faster than the rate at which the context evolves. Therefore, organisations must be sceptical of any increase in process weight that may obstruct the ability of the team to deploy necessary fixes. The tendency towards process bloat is also self-perpetuating and difficult to reverse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The context in which all information systems operate is evolving faster than ever. External dependencies such as the cloud are updated on a near daily basis. User expectations of the power and simplicity of technology are also growing exponentially. Systems which are trapped in a vicious circle of bureaucracy and complexity will fall further and further behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must create quality control processes that are as nimble and fast as they are robust and thorough. Indeed, quality control processes should be as concerned with the fixes they don&amp;rsquo;t make as those that they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 . The nature of Form and Context is explored in more detail by Christopher Alexander in his book about Architectural Design &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Notes_on_the_Synthesis_of_Form&#34;&gt;‘Notes on the Synthesis of Form.&#39;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 reasons innovation is needed more than ever</title>
      <link>https://harrymccarney.com/post/5-reasons-innovation-is-needed-more-than-ever/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://harrymccarney.com/post/5-reasons-innovation-is-needed-more-than-ever/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Plato once said: “necessity is literally the mother of invention” and he continues to be correct. There is increasing evidence that the lockdown is a catalyst for a huge wave of innovation across industry, business, and everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are 5 reasons why you should focus on innovation during the lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://harrymccarney.com/plato.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Plato&amp;rsquo;s mother of necessity&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;1-the-world-is-becoming-more-agile&#34;&gt;1. The world is becoming more agile&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Progress has always been driven by adversity. Crisis is a powerful catalyst for new paradigms to emerge and it’s clear that the current COVID-19 crisis will be no different. Massive new laboratories with hundreds of scientists working on vaccines have been set up in a matter of weeks across the UK. Automotive companies such as Jaguar Land Rover are now partnering with medical device companies to create ventilators. Even the UK parliament is using video conferences to hold debates. In normal times these changes would have taken many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This agile response demonstrates that even highly regulated sectors like health, government and manufacturing can innovate at speed when risk assessments tip the scales from bureaucracy towards adaptability. The behavioural shift we’re witnessing will manifest in millions of small decisions and interactions between people who now adopt collective responsibility for a solution, rather than working to rule on one of its parts. This form of collaboration is the very essence of innovation. It’s also what Agile and Lean consultants have been advocating, with limited success, until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can hope that this way of working will continue and the ‘corona spirit’ will become synonymous with creative collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-extra-bandwidth-for-innovation&#34;&gt;2. Extra bandwidth for Innovation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key obstacles to innovation is Business As Usual (BAU). BAU can absorb all available time and energy and much needed innovation projects are placed on the back burner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have an unprecedented opportunity right now to use time for innovation over BAU. Even those companies that are coping well with the lockdown are quieter than usual and therefore staff have extra time to concentrate creative energy on innovation projects. There will never be a better time to revisit those ideas and projects which you had been too busy to address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-long-term-behavioural-changes-demand-innovation&#34;&gt;3. Long term behavioural changes demand innovation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now know that leaving the house isn’t strictly necessary. Reports in the press about the effect of the coronavirus lockdown on everything from music to friendship may be overplayed but it’s clear that this reconfiguration of everyday life will leave a lasting effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people have learned to use internet banking and order food online. Remote working and Zoom meetups are also here to stay. This fundamental shift in behaviour, and accompanying digital training will create increased demand for more automated and self serve services. Businesses that rely on face to face contact have begun to look archaic and consumers will demand ‘digital first’ experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Projects like HS2, and all the businesses that would spring up around it, suddenly look on the wrong side of history. And house prices…The mega real estate in London which inflates the whole UK property market will become a ghost town as staff are able to work remotely from more affordable rural locations. These changes will have profound and far reaching effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;4-processes-need-to-become-lockdown-proof&#34;&gt;4. Processes need to become lockdown proof&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crisis has cast a bright light on the ‘points of failure’ in our economy. Many industries are now looking at how they can make their processes more resilient to disruption. In short, we need lockdown-proof businesses and innovative solutions are needed to make this happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supply chain in particular has buckled under the pressure of increased demand and decreased product availability. Whether it’s delays with the availability of PPE, or the shutdown of online supermarkets that failed to scale up to the increased demand, this stress testing has revealed many opportunities to create more efficient and robust processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing needs to become less reliant on large numbers of workers working at the same location. At Hack and Craft we have already seen an increased interest in our industrial simulation technology which helps model the effect of process changes before they are rolled out in more costly real life trials.This technology and others will introduce deeper process automation and address the critical points of failure highlighted by the COVID-19 crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;5-tougher-competition-will-demand-innovation&#34;&gt;5. Tougher competition will demand innovation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is certain that the competitive landscape will become tougher. Companies dependent on pre-coronavirus processes will be forced to price in contingency plans and inevitably pass the cost to their customers. Also, the quality of products and services produced by lockdown exposed companies will inevitably decrease leading to a loss of market share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, businesses that innovate away their exposure to lockdown risk will maintain or even reduce prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pressure, combined with the market’s increased digital savvy, will mean customers will quickly switch to more competitive companies. Winning companies will be those that very rapidly adopt lockdown beating technology capable of maintaining high quality production at competitive prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Covid-19 has triggered a new wave of innovation. In the near future we will be able to trace the origin of essential technology and systems back to these turbulent times.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 rules for Distributed Agile — How H&amp;C gets stuff done.</title>
      <link>https://harrymccarney.com/post/10-rules-for-distributed-agile/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://harrymccarney.com/post/10-rules-for-distributed-agile/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;H&amp;amp;C has been working from home since before it became synonymous with flattening the curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many companies have previously allowed employees to work from home but the need for complex systems to be built by teams of people who don’t ever physically meet is a new challenge. Hopefully this account of how H&amp;amp;C does this will demonstrate that Distributed Agile is not only possible, but actually more efficient than co-located teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-we-got-here&#34;&gt;How we got here&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, this way of working was driven by H&amp;amp;C’s need to hire top notch engineers. As our Berlin office filled, we realised we needed more space. At this time in Berlin there was also a large influx of venture capital into new startups which created huge competition for the best developers. In response to this we opened an office in Barcelona and began hiring developers, effectively splitting the product teams across two locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, we quickly realised that crucial communication gets lost in split location product and engineering teams. Subtle but critical decisions were made in the physical coffee meetings and subsequently lost in the sometimes chaotic video conferences between two packed and echoey meeting rooms. We began thinking there must be a better way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were also greatly influenced by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2006/09/07/a-field-guide-to-developers-2/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; Joel Spolsky article. He argues that all developers and knowledge workers doing &lt;a href=&#34;https://suebehaviouraldesign.com/kahneman-fast-slow-thinking/&#34;&gt;‘System 2’ thinking&lt;/a&gt;, as defined by Nobel prize winning psychologist Daniel Kahneman, should have their own single person office. We realised we could address this, improve channels of communication, and access a wider pool of talent around the world by transferring everyone to home working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://harrymccarney.com/BerlinLondon.png&#34; alt=&#34;Berlin and London&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;10-rules-for-effective-distributed-agile-working&#34;&gt;10 rules for effective Distributed Agile working&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this point on we built the methodology and working practises necessary to make our distributed team exceptionally productive. This established H&amp;amp;C’s now industry-wide reputation for high-quality complex innovation at pace. Here are our top 10 rules of effective distributed agile working. They definitely work for us and I hope they are useful for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;1--take-an-all-or-nothing-approach&#34;&gt;1.  Take an all or nothing approach&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us have had the experience of joining a conference in which all the other participants are sitting in the room together. In these situations it is incredibly difficult to understand what is being agreed as the participants in the room are using communication styles suited to physical f2f meetings which do not transmit clearly over the wire to remote participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When everyone ‘dials in’ the communication style changes so that everyone can contribute. To enable this to work properly, H&amp;amp;C insisted early on that everyone should work from home. We’ve even recreated the same ‘working from home’ environment in our newly renovated UK office in order to preserve this high-resolution communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-distributed-working-does-not-equal-flexitime&#34;&gt;2. Distributed working does not equal flexitime&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people learn we are a distributed company, it’s often assumed that we work with flexitime. In fact, the opposite is true. Because we don’t share space it’s extra important that we share time. We start every day at 8am (yes, this means we don’t hire people with more than a three-hour time zone difference from the UK) with a check-in video conference with everyone in the company. We then split up into parallel conferences for each project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone is then available throughout the day via &lt;a href=&#34;https://slack.com/intl/en-gb/?eu_nc=1&#34;&gt;slack&lt;/a&gt; and spontaneous hangouts. Our projects require constant real time collaboration and working from home makes this easier due to our constant connectivity. Our teams are always ready to join face-to-face virtual meetings. Traditional offices often rely on emails which are slow and asynchronous and getting people to gather up their clobber and trundle along to a meeting room wastes more time. At H&amp;amp;C we work in true real time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-you-can-now-hire-the-best&#34;&gt;3. You can now hire the best&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the greatest advantage of distributed teams is the freedom to set very high standards for new recruits. Hiring talent across four time zones means access to a wide pool of the very best talent. For us, removing restrictions surrounding recruiting only from a small pool of scarce talent within commutable reach of the office has been hugely beneficial. Perhaps one good thing that will emerge from the current situation is that it will encourage traditional companies to adopt distributed working practices, and by extension give them the opportunity to hire world-class talent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;4-always-use-a-camera&#34;&gt;4. Always use a camera&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distributed working doesn’t work if people can’t see each other’s faces. The effectiveness of communication increases tenfold when people use cameras. Many companies are up to speed with Skype for business, but don’t use cameras. As a result, people struggle to clearly communicate on complex or sensitive topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;5-buy-a-top-quality-microphone&#34;&gt;5. Buy a top-quality microphone&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to overstate the importance of good quality audio equipment. If people are struggling to hear you, they will become tired and irritable and crucial information could be lost. I’d advise using our go-to solution, the Jabra Speak 510, which we buy for all new staff and freelancers. Invest in a headset and notice how much keener people are to talk to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;6-write-a-summary-at-the-end-of-each-day&#34;&gt;6. Write a summary at the end of each day&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of each day, our staff send a short email to all members of their team. They include what they did that day, and what they hope to do the next day. This ensures everyone remains in sync. It also marks the end of the day, which is helpful psychologically and is similar to the effect of saying goodbye and leaving the office. It’s also useful preparation for team leads to prepare for the Stand-up meetings the following day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;7-be-spontaneous-and-hold-micro-meetings-when-you-need-them&#34;&gt;7. Be spontaneous and hold micro meetings when you need them&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organising and holding traditional face-to-face meetings in a physical office space is a notorious time sink. From the availability of meeting rooms to ensuring everyone attends, meetings are difficult to keep under half an hour. In practice, we rarely find decisions can’t be made in less than 30 minutes and cutting out this whole process saves a vast amount of time.
In our distributed team, we hold many very short and spontaneous virtual meetings throughout the day. Each project or workstream has a dedicated slack channel with a static Google Meet URL pinned inside. A team member only needs to invite colleagues into the virtual meeting and the whole team can communicate face-to-face in seconds with no fuss. They can then return to their work equally seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;8-write-down-action-points-in-real-time-during-the-meeting&#34;&gt;8. Write down action points in real time during the meeting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a traditional physical meeting one person is asked to take minutes. They will generally do this on a pad or in their laptop and then circulate the meeting minutes via email after the meeting. This is a very leaky way to record agreements and often leads to misunderstandings and lack of follow through. Video conferencing enables you to share screens, even better share a google doc, which all the meeting attendees can edit and comment on during the meeting.
As the discussion proceeds, participants can see the consensus being recorded. Any concerns about phrasing, validity, edits and additions can be raised and sorted then. In this way the minutes are written and agreed as the meeting progresses. This enables a clear unambiguous conclusion and the possibility to begin implementing the agreed actions while the topic is still fresh and the team has momentum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;9-always-share-your-screen&#34;&gt;9. Always share your screen&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s vital for distributed teams using video conferencing. Most meetings will focus on a document, whether that’s excel or a code file. To get the most out of the conversation, everyone needs to have eyes on the subject. A screen share is the easiest way to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;10-remember-that-purpose-creates-trust&#34;&gt;10. Remember that purpose creates trust.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately distributed working has worked very well for H&amp;amp;C because we created a common sense of purpose. The whole company is united in our desire to create the highest quality technology solutions for the most complex problems in manufacturing and industry. We do this by creating an environment that minimises obstructions to the engineers and product designers who produce the real value. This shared sense of purpose is what creates trust, which is the essential ingredient to making distributed work productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this proves useful to organisations currently adapting to remote collaborative working. When COVID-19 is behind us, those organisations that embrace distributed working will come out stronger.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>